Guide to the Manchester Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
- Albums, 1697/98 Feb 8; Series I
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, announcing the ratification of the Treaty for the Neutrality of Neufchâtel. (Printed, almost in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 533) Bern, 1708 May 20 (Box 14, Folder 18)
  - Hurly, an Irishman, to the E of M, asking the latter to intercede for him with the Vice-Roy of Naples, and mentioning a recommendation from Col. Broune. (In French) Naples, 1708 May 22 (Box 14, Folder 19)
  - General Palmes to the E of M, on the affairs of the Elector Palatine and the Duke of Savoy, and on the concentration of 40,000 men at Coblentz under Prince Eugene. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 534) Vienna, 1708 May 30 (Box 14, Folder 20)
  - Thomas Pritchard to the E of M, mentioning the indisposition of the Venetian Ambassador, and consquent difficulty of delivering a box to him and obtaining a receipt. There were great complaints of the scarcity of money in England. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 358) London, 1708 Jun 1 (Box 14, Folder 21)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of Mon the formation of camps at Bussolino and Ivrea, the seizure of Comaccio, and the probable reluctance of other powers to let the Emperor have so good a port in the Adriatic. The Queen of Spain was in Milan. There had been no news of the fleet. Turin, 1708 Jun 2 (Box 14, Folder 22)
  - J. Quinton to the E of M, chiefly on family matters. He had waited on the Duchess of Marlborough "with the patterns" which "pleased her extremely," and she would "give his Lordship more trouble about them." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 359) London, 1708 Jun 3 (Box 14, Folder 23)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, expressing willingness to join with Lord Sunderland in any thing the Earl could desire. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 535) Camp at Torbanck, 1708 Jun 4 (Box 14, Folder 24)
  - Lady Elizabeth Montague [Montagu] to her brother the E of M, on his probable return to England, and on various matters of gossip, e.g., the marriages of friends, etc. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 365), 1708 Jun 8 (Box 14, Folder 25)
  - Henry Newton to the E of M, announcing the capture of a number of French vessels laden with ammunition, etc, by Sir John Lake. Florence, 1708 Jun 9 (Box 14, Folder 26)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, to the effect that he had been engaged in fitting out transports which would be ready on the 5th or 6th of the following month, and have all the troops embarked on them within ten days afterwards. Vado, 1708 Jun 17/28 (Box 14, Folder 27)
  - Paolo Abbate Franceschini to the E of M, thanking him for his patronage and protection. He had met the Secretary of the Imperial Ambassador, from whom he had learned that he might expect a letter from the Duca Moles. (In Italian) Milan, 1708 Jun 20 (Box 14, Folder 28)
  - Alexandre de Bonneval to the E of M, pointing out the advantages of the site of Commacchio for commercial purposes and as a harbour for ships of war. (In French) Commacchio, 1708 Jun 22 (Box 14, Folder 29)
  - Undirected letter of the Duca Moles to the effect that he had presented the Memorial which had been forwarded by the Envoy Stanhope, to "His Majesty" [Charles III of Spain?], who regarded it favourably, and was disposed to grant a pension. (Copy. In Italian. See 31) Barcelona, 1708 May 26 (Box 14, Folder 30)
  - Paolo Abbate Franceschini to the E of M, enclosing a copy of a letter from the Duca Moles, which had been sent to the Abbate by the Imperial Ambassador at Venice, and again thanking the Earl for his protection and recommendation. (In Italian. See 30. Endorsed, "Ab. Franceschini, and one from the D. of Moles."), 1708 Jun 27 (Box 14, Folder 31)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, announcing that the Pope had asked the Catholic Cantons for assistance against the Emperor to defend the Holy See, as the Imperial Troops had invaded the Ferrarese, and that the French Ambassador, M. Puisieulx, was to be succeeded by the Comte de Gerzé. He mentions enclosure of a copy of the Nuncio's Memorial to the Cantons. Bern, 1708 Jun 24 (Box 14, Folder 32)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, acknowledging the receipt of copies of a Memorial of Lord Manchester, and of the Senate's answer to it, and assuring him of the Queen's complete approval of all his proceedings. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 540) Whitehall, 1708 Jun 25 (Box 14, Folder 33)
  - Sir John Norris to the E of M, giving a variety of details of the military position and prospects in Spain, and of the embarcation of troops at Vado. (pp.6) On board the Ranelaugh, with the fleet, at Vado, 1708 Jun 26 (Box 14, Folder 34)
  - G. Germain to the E of M, apologising for his delay in writing, caused by the supposition that the Earl was about to return at once from Venice. He had had the Lord Treasurer, Lord Sunderland, Mr. Boyle, and "le bonne homme Mons. de Spanheim" to dine with him, and they had drunk the Earl's health. (In French) London, 1708 Jun 28 (Box 14, Folder 35)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, congratulating the Earl upon his success at Venice, giving some particulars respecting Prince Eugene and the Duke of Savoy's affairs, and mentioning in a postscript the threatening attitude of "the Swede." (pp. 6) Vienna, 1708 Jun 30 (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, announcing that the religious difficulty in Toggenberg was accommodated, that the Catholic Cantons would probably send 3,000 men to the assistance of the Pope, and that the Duke of Savoy would put in the field an army of 36,000 foot and 8,000 horse. (Printed, in part only, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 540) Bern, 1708 Jul 1 (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, on the introduction of the Elector of Hanover into the Electoral College, and on various matters relating to Imperial politics. (The greater part is printed under date July 7, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 542) Vienna, 1708 Jul 4 (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - The E of M to the Duchess of Marlborough, on the subject of velvets and damasks. (Draft) Venice, 1708 Jul 6 (Box 14, Folder 39)
  - Paolo Franceschini to [the E of M?], announcing that he [had] secured a passage to Vado, and been promised an introduction to Admiral Leake. (In Italian) Genoa, 1708 Jul 8 (Box 14, Folder 40)
  - Thomas Kirke to the E of M, to the effect that a passage to Barcelona had been secured for the Abbate Franceschini on board H.M.S. Defiance. Genoa, 1708 Jul 8 (Box 14, Folder 41)
  - The Duca du Moles to the E of M, expressing pleasure at having been able to use his influence to procure a pension for the Abbate Franceschini from the King of Spain. (In Italian) Barcelona, 1708 Jul 9 (Box 14, Folder 42)
  - C. Cole to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of various letters, and touching on various rumours and matters of gossip. (Printed, in part, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 544) Venice, 1708 Jul 14 (Box 14, Folder 43)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, giving some particulars of the battle of Oudenarde. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 544) Camp at Wervick, 1708 Jul 15 (Box 14, Folder 44)
  - General Palmes to the E of M, conveying news of the French defeat at Oudenarde. Vienna, 1708 Jul 18 (Box 14, Folder 45)
  - M. Runkel to a person addressed as "Monsieur" [Mr. Stanyan], giving particulars of the battle of Oudenarde. (In French. Copy. See 48 and 49) Schaffhausen, 1708 Jul 20 (Box 14, Folder 46)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, giving some particulars of the embarcation at Vado, and mentioning the success of Mr. [General] Palmes in securing the investiture of Montferrat for the Duke of Savoy. (Printed in part in Cole's Memoirs, p. 545) Genoa, 1708 Jul 20 (Box 14, Folder 47)
  - M. Runkel's paper, giving fuller details of the news conveyed in his letter of the 20th July. (In French. 7 pages. Copy.) Schaffhausen, 1708 Jul 21 (Box 14, Folder 48)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of copies of letters from the Dutch Minister at Schaffhausen, in the Victory at Oudenarde. (See 46 and 48) Bern, 1708 Jul 22 (Box 14, Folder 49)
  - J. Addison to the E of M, mentioning the arrest of the Muscovite Ambassador by bailiffs, expressing strong hopes of the success of the combined operations against France, congratulating the Earl on the approbation given to his conduct at Venice, etc. (Printed in part in Cole's Memoirs, 546) Cockpit, 1708 Jul 23 (Box 14, Folder 50)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, conveying the Queen's approval of Lord Manchester's prudent conduct at Venice, and mentioning the enclosure of a letter of recall to be used as Lord Manchester might see fit. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 545) Whitehall, 1708 Jul 23 (Box 14, Folder 51)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, expressing his belief that it would be difficult to make the Court of Vienna "go a different pace from what it thinks fittest to go." There was, however, a King whose "Gothic politics" made their councils "a little uneasy and uncertain." It was to be hoped the Duke [of Marlborough] would "set us up in the world again." Vienna, 1708 Jul 23 (Box 14, Folder 52)
  - The Duchess of Marlborough to [the E of M], on the subject of velvets and damasks. Windsor Castle, 1708 Aug 5 (Box 14, Folder 53)
  - Sir John Norris to the E of M, conveying the information that he had landed the troops at Barcelona, and giving various particulars relating to the probable course of the campaign in the Peninsula. (5 pages. A part is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 545) Ranelaugh, with the fleet, 1708 Jul 26 (Box 14, Folder 54)
  - The E of M to the Lord Treasurer, asking to be named Plenipotentiary, in the event of a peace with France. His dispute at Venice had been at last adjusted. (Draft. Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 373) Venice, 1708 Jul 27 (Box 14, Folder 55)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, explaining how he had lost money by the opera, giving details of the buildings at Blenheim, etc., and mentioning that the Duchess of Marlborough was "mighty well at Court, but the Q.'s fondness of t'other lady was not to be expressed." (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 377) London, 1708 Jul 27 (Box 14, Folder 56)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, giving further particulars relating to the battle of Oudenarde and its results. Bern, 1708 Jul 29 (Box 14, Folder 57)
  - E. Lewis to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a lampoon said to have been made by Mr. M...r, and congratulating him upon his approaching return to England. Whitehall, 1708 Jul 30 (Box 14, Folder 58)
  - The Duchess of Marlborough to the E of M, thanking him very warmly for the trouble he had already taken, and giving very full details of the velvets, damasks, etc, which she wished to have sent to her. (Printed in Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 387) Windsor Castle, 1708 Aug 1 (Box 14, Folder 59)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Marlborough, congratulating him upon the victory of Oudenarde, making some comments upon the general military situation, and expressing his anxiety to leave Venice. (Draft) Venice, 1708 Aug 3 (Box 14, Folder 60)
  - A paper unsigned and unaddressed, giving an account of the disembarcation of troops at Barcelona, and of the military situation in Spain. (In French) Barcelona, 1708 Aug 4 (Box 14, Folder 61)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, mentioning enclosure of a paper in French, and giving some details of the disposition of forces in Flanders and on the Rhine. Bern, 1708 Aug 5 (Box 14, Folder 62)
  - The E of M to Lord Halifax, complaining of an attack made upon his gondola at Venice, and explaining the necessity of having some public satisfaction. (Draft. the particulars are given at greater length in the Earl's letters to Sunderland, dated May 30, and April 6, and printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 519 and p. 521) Venice, 1708 Apr 6 (Box 14, Folder 63)
  - The Duchess of Marlborough to the E of M "I have received the honour of Your Lordship's letter...and I am sure ...your papers will be of great use..." Windsor Castle, 1708 Aug 10 (Box 14, Folder 64)
  - Paolo Abbate Franceschini to the E of M, announcing that he had seen the British Envoy, General Stanhope, and the Duca Moles, and that his promised pension was to issue out of lands in Italy, from which he would probably receive nothing for years. He askes for a further recommendation from the Earl, and mentions the arrival of the fleet and troops at Barcelona. (In Italian.) Barcelona, 1708 Aug 11 (Box 14, Folder 65)
  - W. Chetwynd to the E of M, announcing that he concluded he would be Resident at Genoa, and mentions the arrival of the fleet and troops at Barcelona. (In Italian) Barcelona, 1708 Aug 11 (Box 14, Folder 66)
  - E. Howe to the E of M, describing the position of the forces in the Rhine. Muhlberg, 1708 Aug 11 (Box 14, Folder 67)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, describing the difficulties of the mountain passes, and expressing hopes of a successful campaign. Chaumont, 1708 Aug 2/13 (Box 14, Folder 68)
  - Unsigned letter to the E of M on the state of the Court, a quarrel between the Duchess of Marlborough and the Lord Chamberlain, and the probability that the Earl might obtain the Lord Chamberlain's Post. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 383) London, 1708 Aug 14 (Box 14, Folder 69)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, expressing hopes that the Campaign would be followed by an honourable and lasting peace. (Printed, Cole's Memoirs, p. 546) Camp at Helchin, 1708 Aug 15 (Box 14, Folder 70)
  - J. Vanbrugh to the E of M, on the re-building at Kimbolton, and on operatic affairs. (Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 383) Biggleswade, 1708 Aug 17 (Box 14, Folder 71)
  - W. Chetwynd to the E of M, mentioning enclosure from Sir J. Norris on the state of affairs in Spain. The Emperor would be asked to send 4,000 foot out of the forces in Italy, but it was not expected that he would consent. Five men-of-war had touched at Genoa, and just been despatched, Chetwynd had sent with them 50,000 pistoles for Mr. Stanhope. Thr money might "be able to stop many a man's mouth, and raise their spirits," of which there was need. Genoa, 1708 Aug 18 (Box 14, Folder 72)
  - Sir John Norris to the E of M, describing the capture of "Callery" [Cagliari]. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 547 "Ranelaugh, near Callery", 1708 Aug 18 (Box 14, Folder 73)
  - A. Stanyan to the E of M, giving particulars of the various military movements as reported to him. Bern, 1708 Aug 19 (Box 14, Folder 74)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, announcing the commencement of the siege of Lille. (Printed. Cole's Memoirs, p. 547) Camp at Amongies, 1708 Aug 26 (Box 14, Folder 75)
  - Sir P. Medows to the E of M, giving an account of the reinforcements to be sent by the Emperor to serve under General Staremberg in Spain, togher with some particulars of the unsatisfactory plight of the Hanoverians and Würtembergers. Vienna, 1708 Sep 1 (Box 14, Folder 76)
  - General Palmes to the E of M, describing some of the movements of the Duke of Savoy, who was not expected to march beyond Fenestrelles for some time. Turin, 1708 Sep 5 (Box 14, Folder 77)
  - J. Chetwynd to the E of M, informing him that as Fenestrelles had fallen, nothing further would be undertaken by the Duke of Savoy until another year. (Printed, in part, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 547) Camp at Mantoule, near Fenestrelles, 1708 Sep 7 (Box 14, Folder 78)
  - The Earl of Sunderland to the E of M, congratulating him upon the satisfactory termination of the affair at Venice. (Printed, nearly in full, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 551) Whitehall, 1708 Sep 14 (Box 14, Folder 79)
  - The E of M to the Duchess of Marlborough, on the damasks, velvets, etc. which he had been purchasing for her, etc. (Draft. Printed in "Court and Society from Elizabeth to Anne," ii, 389) Venice, 1708 Sep 14 (Box 14, Folder 80)
  - The E of M to the Duke of Marlborough, announcing that he was about to have his audience of leave on the following day. The British fleet had gone to Port Mahon. Nothing untoward was to be apprehended except only that the promised reinforcements would not be sent by the Emperor from Naples to Spain by reason of the dispute with the Pope. The Republic of Venice would not "concern themselves till they saw a sure game." Venice (Box 14, Folder 81)
  - The E of M to the Earl of Sunderland, mentioning enclosure of the speech made at his last audience of the Doge. The fleet had sailed for Minorca. (Draft. Printed, with some variations, in Cole's Memoirs, p. 549) Venice, 1708 Sep 21 (Box 14, Folder 82)
  - Translation of the answer made to the last speech of the E of M by the Senate. (A translation, substantially the same, but differently worded, is printed in Cole's Memoirs, p. 552) Venice, 1708 Oct 1 (Box 14, Folder 83)
  - The E of M to the Lord Treasurer, to the effect that he was about to return home by way of Hanover and Holland, and that the dispute between the Emperor and the Pope appeared to be gainig strength. (Draft) Venice, 1708 Oct 5 (Box 14, Folder 84)
  - The E of M to the Earl of Sunderland, alleging that the attack on his boat had been made at the instigation of the Inquisitor Ruzzini, and asking for a credential letter to be presented by Mr. Cole to the College. (Draft. Printed with some variations in Cole's Memoirs, p. 551) Venice, 1708 Oct 5 (Box 14, Folder 85)
  - The Principe di Chiusano to the E of M, wishing the Earl a prosperous journey to London, and requesting to have his own respects conveyed to the Duke of Marlborough in Flanders. (In Italian) Naples, 1708 Oct 9 (Box 14, Folder 86)
  - The Marquis de Prié to the E of M. The squadron for the transport of troops from Naples to Barcelona had arrived at Leghorn on the 29th of the previous month. Cardinal Grimani, the Viceroy of Naples, however, was of opinion that it might be with advantage detained in Italian waters, as there did not appear to be a necessity for large reinforcements in Spain. Great vigilance would be required to thwart the schemes of the French in favour of an Italian league with the Pope. Marshal de Tessé had not, however, as yet been very successful, and it did not seem probable that he would have better fortune at Venice than elsewhere. De Prié himself had been sent to Rome by the Emperor, with the object of inducing the Pope to disarm. (In French) Rome, 1708 Oct 7 (Box 14, Folder 87)
  - R. Powys to the E of M, on money matters. Whitehall, 1708 Oct 26 (Box 14, Folder 88)
  - A Statement of accounts. Venice, 2708 Oct 5 (Box 14, Folder 89)
  - The E of M to the Earl of Sunderland, describing his journey homewards. He would probably travel with the Duke of Marlborough after leaving the Hague, and asked for a yacht for his voyage to England. He thanked Lord Sunderland for having "settled Mr. Cole at Venice." (Draft) Hanover, 1708 Nov 9 (Box 14, Folder 90)
  - The E of M to the Earl of Sunderland, mentioning a report that Brussels was invested by the Elector of Bavaria. (Draft) The Hague, 1708 Nov 23 (Box 14, Folder 91)
  - The E of M to Mr. Secretary Boyle, to the effect that there was great joy in Holland at the crossing of the Scheldt by the Duke of Marlborough, and the relief of Brussels. It is now plain wherever the Duke marches the enemy will retire as fast as they can." The Dutch were disposed to continue the war and augment their forces. There had been an exchange of courtesies between the Earl and the Muscovite Ambassador. (Draft) The Hague, 1708 Nov 23 (Box 14, Folder 92)
  - The Duke of Marlborough to the E of M, expressing regret that he would not be able to meet the Earl in Holland, and mentioning the affair of the Scheldt, and the good news that the Elector [of Bavaria] had been "obliged to raise the siege of Brussels very shamefully" Alost, 1708 Nov 30 (Box 14, Folder 93)
  - R. Powys to the E of M, enclosing statements of accounts, etc, and statements of the allowances to the Earl of Ranelaugh, as paymaster of the forces, and to Mr. Howe., 1708 Dec 25 (Box 14, Folder 94-95)
  - Speech made in the College at Venice by Mr. Cole, Her Majesty's Secretary there, on presentation of Credentials. (In Italian) Venice, 1708 Dec 17 (Box 14, Folder 96)
  - The E of M to the Duchess of Marlborough, on the subject of velvets and damasks. (Draft) (Box 14, Folder 97)
  - Reply to the answer made by the Court of Vienna to the Memorial of the E of M on the subject of the claims of the Duke of Savoy. (Copy, pp. 6. In French), n.d. (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - An unsigned and undated statement concerning politics and military movements on the Continent. The "army of Guebrian" was "in great straits." The King of France was not expected to live, though his health was somewhat improved by "using the waters of Forges." The Jesuits were growing "mighty insolent." ...Then follow some further small details of foreign politics and military movements, along which occurs the following passage: "It is certain there have been fiery and bloody apparitions of rods and a sword seen again over the city of Leipzig which always have portended some great action or other." There had been a happy conclusion of the great meeting at the Hague. The Prince of Orange would be "kept under," and the common good of the Netherlands "advanced and secured. The Parliament of England had cause to rejoice at this good news." (pp. 7) Paris and Amsterdam (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Treaty of Neutrality of the Duchy and County of Burgundy, between Louis XIII of France, and Phillip III of Spain. (In French. Copy. pp. 23) Paris, 1610 Dec 31 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Captain General Domenico Moconigo to Captain General da Mar on commercial regulations affecting the islands of Zante and Cephalonia. (In Italian) "Romania", 1691 Dec 10 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - First speech of Lord Fauconberge to the Duke and Senate of Venice. (Copy) Venice (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Extracts (apparently) from the correspondence of Sir Henry Wotton (Ambassador at Venice in 1609) and Sir Dudley Carleton (Ambassador at Venice in 1610), touching the honours due to Ambassadors upon their reception at Venice. Venice, 1609-10 (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Speech of the English resident upon reception and presentation of Credentials at Venice. (Copy) Venice (Box 15, Folder 7)
  - Answer of the Senate to the speech of Lord Fauconberge, English Ambassador at Venice, when taking leave. (Copy) Venice, n.d. (Box 15, Folder 8)
  - Abstract of negotiations at Venice from 1560 to 1639, giving the names of the English Residents and Ambassadors. (24 pages), 1560-1639 (Box 15, Folder 9)
  - Statement of the case of Mr. Hayles, English Consul at Venice in respect of "consolage" dues of that port., 1670 (Box 15, Folder 10)
  - Instructions to Sir Thomas Higgons, Envoy Extraordinary to the Republic of Venice. (Copy) Whitehall, 1673 (Box 15, Folder 11)
  - Memorial of Marie Cardin, widow of Elie Genays (laundress in ordinary of the Queen Dowager of England) to the King of France. Her goods had been seized as if she had been one of the fugitives from France, who were affected by the Revocation of the Edict of Nantes. She had, however, a brevet de congé (recited) which was dated Oct. 26, 1682, and she prayed relief. The memorial was, according to the endorsement, to be placed in the hands of the English Ambassador. (In French) (Box 15, Folder 12)
  - Hugh Broughton to the Duke of Shrewsbury, on the circumstances of his reception as English consul at Venice. The letter concludes with an anecdote of the Conte della Torre, who died of vexation at the manner in which he was treated by the College. (Three very large closely- written pages) Venice, 1696/96 (Box 15, Folder 13)
  - List of Secretaries and Under Secretaries of State, and of the Household apparently of James II when living at St. Germains. (Box 15, Folder 14)